this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this episode of software
engineering radio is sponsored by data
dog data dog is a monitoring platform
that helps thousands of companies get
visibility into cloud infrastructure
optimized application performance and
avoid downtime data dog integrates with
more than 200 technologies so you can
get immediate insights into all of your
databases your web servers cloud
services and container technologies like
docker and kubernetes start a free trial
today at dado dog comm / se radio for
software engineering radio this is
Robert bloomin today I have with me Ed
Santorelli Edson is a senior principal
software engineer at Red Hat where he is
the JBoss drools / Red Hat VRMs project
lead medicine is responsible for the
roadmap architecture development and
delivery of the drools product Hudson is
also a researcher with a focus on
artificial intelligence and rules
engines Edson welcome to software
engineering radio thank you Robert thank
you for having me here today
Edson and I will be talking about rules
engines but before we start that soon
would you like to tell those sinners any
more information about yourself that I
didn't cover no I think it's very much
that I've been working for a long time
for the last about 12 years in the
drills project it's a passion of mine
and it's it's it's something that really
interested me so always happy to talk
about it
great let's start with some basic
prerequisites what is a business rule a
business rule
is something that is define it or or is
used by by a business to execute the
process or to make a decision an example
of a business rule could be for instance
the tax rate on a given product that the
company sells or for instance a policy
the company says you know customers
older than a given age will receive a
discount so those are examples of
business rules business rules must be
quite important in the operation of a
business is that the case it is no
business can operate without following
its own policies and rules or even
government laws do business rules have
any internal structure you drill down
into a rule yes it's very common to have
a condition or a set of conditions and
then a set of consequences derive it
from those conditions there are
different types of business rules but
that's the general structure can you
give me an example yes for instance in
the example of a company policy that
says customers older than 60 years or 60
years older or more will have you know
50% discount on the ticket for shows
this is a set of conditions the customer
has to have 60 years of age or older
and the consequence of those conditions
is he gets 50 percent discount on the
ticket okay rules have two parts then
there's the conditions when the rule
applies and consequence which is
something that happens or a value or say
a bit more what is the about the
consequence part is it an action or a
value or a number it's both when we are
talking about the traditional business
rules they are called production rules
they have usually an action or more
associated to that when we are talking
about decision services that is a
separate part of the business rules
discipline then decision services
usually return a
so they are both business rules they're
both styles of business rules when our
business rules applied or executed when
the condition is met typically it
defines a scenario and whenever that
scenario is found when those conditions
are fulfilled the business rule executes
I'm familiar with many systems that are
request driven for example ecommerce the
person is checking out their shopping
cart at that time I might want to know
is the customer entitled to any
discounts or what is the tax rate on the
customers order our business rules
executed on a on demand basis as a
service yes that's a very common case
and this is what is called the decision
services so you have something happening
for instance the customer is clicking
checkout on the website that triggers
the execution of that service to decide
about something there is also other
types of business rules that are
triggered by conditions in in real time
or in batch processes could you go into
the real time case a bit more the real
time case is more about when you are
monitoring or the system is monitoring
conditions and it receives events that
trigger those actions an example would
be for instance in logistics where
you're monitoring your traffic your your
your trucks and you receive traffic
alerts if there is an accident for
instance in a given intersection and you
have a truck heading towards that you
might react to that event the accident
and reroute the truck into a different
Road where that is free that is open
basically something I see a lot in my
job in DevOps is we have alert setup
where if CPU load is greater than 60% on
this instance for five minutes we page
on coppers in to investigate would that
be a good
example that's a great example this
heads more towards another discipline
inside the business rules called complex
event processing where you're monitoring
systems in real time and then you take
actions on those systems so this is also
a very common and very important use
case for business rules ok that sounds
like something I want to come back to
but I want to go on more into the basic
cover all systems so it sounds like a
set of rules would apply depending on
the situation like a customer checkout
or can this person be approved to get a
loan how many rules does a business have
maybe give a range what's a very small
number what is a large number of rules
it depends really on on how how much the
business can automate but the typical
case would be a few thousand rules for a
small case several you know thousands of
thousands for a median case and the
largest cases I worked with they had a
you know about a million rules or more
Wow
that's gonna raise some very interesting
questions about implementation which
we'll get to later right now I'd like to
delve into our main topic what is a
rules engine a rules engine is a
specialized component of meat or that
can that is capable of executing rules
the easiest way I have to explain is
make an analogy to a database that is
very common for all you know software
engineers a database allows you to
extract data from the application and
manage the data lifecycle externally you
can do you know optimizations the
algorithms in the database can execute
tasks much better than if you would
implement those tasks yourself in
application code so a rules engine is
the same thing but for business rules it
allows you to extract those business
rules that could be implemented in you
know in the imperative language you
extract them treat them as data to the
system in
manage the lifecycle of those rules
independently the rules engine also in
runtime has optimizations that allow the
engine to execute those rules more
efficiently okay and it's in how are the
rules expressed by the program or to the
rules engine there are several ways we
call them metaphors very common
metaphors are decision tables they can
be you know they are just tables where
each rule each row on the table is a
rule but you can use specialized
languages we support several of them our
native language is called DRL it's a
declarative language would it be fair to
call that a domain-specific language for
the rules domain we do support
domain-specific languages and as you
know it's called DSL because then you
can make them really specific to the
domain of the customer we usually call
the the native language a technical
language because it's it's really
technical it's more for programmers
finder study then you're saying that
suppose the domain is insurance you can
develop or implement an insurance
specific DSL on top of the base language
that Drule supports that's correct okay
would you call it would be fair to call
the base language a domain-specific
language for rules in general I haven't
seen it called that way but I guess it's
it's a it's a DSL for rules yes it is
it's a bit more technical than the
typical DSL that I've I know of but yes
why would I want to code we can write
business rules in any well-known
programming language I'm sure every
programmer has written rules like you
just entered age on a web form let's
verify the age is a number that it's a
positive number that it's less than 150
why would I want a specialized language
for writing rule
because you switch usually when you
implement in the application code it's
typically imperative languages you know
Java JavaScript C++ whatever and when
you implement those in a traditional
rules engine you are using a declarative
language in declarative languages as you
know you only say what you want to do
not how you want to do the rules engine
is responsible for figuring out how to
do that tasks how to match and execute
that rule we did a show on declarative
languages recently in relation to
infrastructure mm-hmm why is a
declarative approach a good approach for
rules what are the benefits of that for
a starter it's more productive you can
do more in less time but the main reason
I would say is because it allows the
engine to do what it does best optimize
and decide how to execute your rules in
the best possible way okay I want to
come back to that in a minute but first
one more question about the language on
software teams with very rules intensive
applications do you typically have a one
or a few programmers who specialize in
the rules language and work with
business analysts or does everyone learn
it and it becomes like embedding sequel
in your web based database application
where it's a skill that generally
everyone has this is very specific to
the dynamic of each team because there
are metaphors and there are languages
for rules that are higher-level and
targeted at business users or you know
well slightly technical business user
just to mention an example there is a
standard called decision model and
notation DMM that is very high level
targets business users and they can
develop the rules themselves and there
are very technical languages on the
other side of the spectrum in the case
of the native language that really
requires developers to work
with that language it's based on Java so
it's very familiar to Java developers
but it's it's a technical language this
is a common issue how did the business
and engineering work together we're
software engineers we don't know whether
somebody should be given a loan or an
insurance policy or not the business is
going to define that to us there's an
impedance mismatch or there can be
between how business understands their
business and how we write the code how
does the technology does it help bridge
that impedance mismatch absolutely in
and this is one of the Holy Grails that
that we we target with this kind of
technology and this kind of methodology
and when you look at the higher level
languages like dmn or like decision
tables those are the abstractions that
allow business users and developers to
speak the same language to understand
each other and look at the model and see
in both understand this is what is being
executed in it is it does match what the
requirement what the description of the
business rules are great and now I'd
like to come back to the run time which
you mentioned a moment ago I want to
start with a simple case suppose a
business has one rule how would the
rules engine execute that one rule well
it it would just you know try to match
the scenario and execute that rule okay
could you walk us through a simple
example of somebody's requesting alone
and we have a rule about their income it
has to be greater than $20,000 to get
the loan so how would the rules engine
operate on that we work with what we
call fats effect is basically a data
object so the data object would have you
know the customer application and would
have an attribute there that attribute
would be the income and the rule says if
the income is larger than 20,000 then it
would execute an action for instance
consider the law
right but the rules engine compiles that
roll into a data structure and that's an
optimized data structure it's it's not
like an if-then-else in in a program
typical programming language that data
structure is responsible for actually
you know executing checking those
conditions and then executing the
actions if those conditions match
sometimes these questions don't work
great on an audio podcast can you say
any more about the data structure yes
what it looks like but to do that I will
use a slightly more complicated example
imagine that you have a customer data
type that has for instance the status of
the customer VIP for instance or you
know a gold customer silver and etc so
imagine you have 10 different values for
that customer and then imagine you have
10 different rules for each of those
values right so basically if you were
implementing these into a typical rules
engine you would have a hundred
different if clause in your Java program
for instance right so based on the tier
of the customer they get a different
preferential price for example for for
example and then you know a different
shipping rate and etc each of those is a
condition so basically you you would
have if you were implementing Java 100
different earths in there 10 different
values times 10 rules per value you
would have a hundred so in Java when a
computer is executing that program or in
imperative language it would check every
one of those ifs one by one and then the
ones that match execute the condition
write a rules engine compiles those
rules and checks what is common between
them and indexes them in memory so
instead of checking 100 FS one by one
that data structure aggregates those
similar values those ten similar values
into only ten clauses and then index
them so that it doesn't even two
execute even Dalston it just understands
that if this customer has a type VIP
then only that rule that set of rules
who match and then it will only execute
that check once so this is the kind of
optimization the rules engine we will
start doing behind the scenes if I
understand its it might be like a
database where the simple way to search
is search every single record which
results in a table scan you have an
index where based on the value falls in
between certain ranges it can go
directly to a segment or an area on disk
where those records are as I understand
something exactly the same is that a
good analogy for what that's actually a
great analogy it's a much better way of
explaining than I did so thank you ok
now a moment ago you mentioned that the
rows engine has access to facts like the
customers income or their age or the
tier the gold or platinum tier where do
those facts come from they come from the
application so from a rules engine
perspective we have adapters to
different data sources and we integrate
with you know projects like camo
that will bring that data into the
system so they exist in databases in
files or if it's a rest service you know
observes it will come as a request and
then that data is Marsh unmarshal dand
then input inserted into the engine so
the engine can do the devaluation I see
broadly speaking then the facts could
come from the request or any type of
persistent store or non persistent store
I have where there's facts or attributes
that I consider relevant to this
situation that's correct
ok great I would like to get to more
complex case more realistic what happens
how does the rule engine work when you
have a lot of rules you said you could
have thousands or tens of thousands what
changes the algorithm that compiles
those rules into a data structure is
very efficient for increasing number of
rules
so the best way I think to describe the
scenario is that for an increasing
number of rules the order of complexity
of the rules is constant so when you
have a knowledge base or rule base with
1,000 rules and when you have a
knowledge base with 100,000 rules
typically the response time for any
rules execution will be very similar
will be constant so for increasing
number of rules we don't increase the
response time okay the engine then it
has a way of organizing their rules
efficiently so it doesn't have to
execute or search every single rule for
every single fact that's correct so that
internal data structure is basically a
discrimination tree and then it will
organize and index the rules so you
actually have a very efficient solution
for increasing number of rules okay now
let's say where we're trying to
determine if the applicant will be
granted their insurance policy maybe
rules on age their health their income
where they live their zip code how does
the engine determine what order to
execute these rules or does it do them
in parallel it depends on the way the
rules are declared because users can
define priorities so rules that have
higher priority or have a difference if
ik they will be executed first but if no
priority is given or if the same
priority applies to a group of rules
then the rules engine will execute them
in in the way that it optimizes the most
so whatever way has the best
optimization is the way that the rules
engine will execute them so it would be
an example if we had a rule of if your
income is greater than a million dollars
that would immediately eliminate the
vast majority of the applicants
then you might want to execute that rule
first because it could result in that
you don't have to do any more rules
after that yes that that would be a
higher priority rule but if an applicant
has a income lower than that it will not
be not even touch that rule the rules
engine notes this and it will it will
not even try to execute that rule and it
knows that because it's built this index
type structure correct
okay now you talked about customer might
be in the gold tier or the silver tier
could you have rules that chain on the
results of other rules like for example
we have a role it says if you've done
ten transactions with this company you
spend more than $100 we're going to
classify you as a gold customer then we
have another rule says Gold customers
get 10% discount so you have to execute
those two rules in a certain order does
the engine figure that ordering out yes
and this is a great example this is
called chaining and the mechanism is is
called inference so if if a rule changes
the values or understands that those
values affect the reasoning about other
rules those other rules will be chained
and executed after and there are two
types of chaining right okay so I do
want to ask you about the two types of
chain you one other question that we
have a rule that determines that the
customer is a gold customer and now that
becomes a fact so rules in US in this
case can have I mean another language
programming situation I might call this
side effects where they change facts and
then those facts affect other rules is
that right yes that's correct that's
perfect okay so is it really a good idea
to have a whole programming model based
on side effects well the side effect in
this case is local and it's it makes the
development of assistance much easier
right so it's not a side effect that is
persisted it can be persisted but it
usually it's not it's local it's
part of the reasoning process so why it
makes much the system much easier to
develop is because you don't need to
think about everything at once each role
is independent but the rules engine will
will find out those dependencies
implicitly and will chain them together
implicitly I see if I didn't have that
engine inside fact and I would have to
think about what are all the possible
outputs of this one chunk of code and
then finish computing all of those and
then call another chunk of code it would
put all that complexity on to me as the
programmer exactly so in your example
using the mindset of the developer all
the developer has to do is say well
there is a rule here that says if there
are more than 10 transactions this is a
gold customer that's all he needs to
think about and then he looks at the
requirements document and the
requirement says if it's a gold customer
receives 10% discount that's all he
needs to think and the rules engine will
will find those relationships and
execute them and in order as as
necessary is it a problem in practice
that you could have side-effects
chaining in such a way that it never
converged to a solution it is possible
it is a you know Turing complete
language but there are mechanisms that
allow us to control this and minimize
the risks of this happening I also as
any you know software engineering
methodology you go to tests to make sure
that you are not reaching an deflate
loop or or something similar to that
okay okay so this is not a question but
a comment than if we had five thousand
rules I could see that as a human being
I could maybe understand or a steam of
several people could understand all
those rules if each rule is fairly
simple like the person who has ten
transactions is a goal customer but to
try to understand all the dependencies
between those as a human that
impossible it is it is not supposed you
would not have to worry about this
because the engine does this for you but
a very common requirement is to have
audit logs on all those decisions so
basically what you do is you submit a
case to the ancient the ancient responds
with a set of values and an audit log
why that decision was made and indeed
the audit log you can see oh this
customer had more than 10 transactions
so it was classified as a gold customer
and that activated that other rule for
gold customers and that gave him the
discount so the audit log is a very
common requirement that is provided by
the engine itself if anyone then has a
question why did we why this person was
denied alone and there may be laws in
that state about discrimination that you
could show that you applied certain
rules and that those rules are all
compliant with the regulation and that
the rules are applied consistently to
everyone and no one was singled out for
worse treatment things like that
absolutely this is this is a very common
use case this podcast is supported by
Atlantic net hosting solution provider
of healthcare HIPAA PCI compliance and
AD tech if you're feeling the pain of
having outdated technology call
atlanticnet and get the latest security
firewall intrusion detection backup
disaster recovery and virtualization or
if you're starting a new project or not
getting the results you want from your
current providers atlanticnet can help
you succeed the fully audited solutions
in 23 years in business they won't let
you down
visit atlanticnet to learn more
[Music]
okay back to you were talking about a
moment ago that you you test the rules
is it realistic when you have this many
rules to come up with a decent set of
test cases that covers enough different
combinations that you've got a good
assurance that it will work yes it is
common to have things that that people
or that companies do or they take for
instance snapshots of their production
data and save those snapshots and then
because the results are known for those
snapshots they can rerun that at every
release to make sure they are not having
regressions that the rules are behaving
as they should so this is usually how
that's done
the idea of test-driven development very
popular if I had a rule set of 3,000
rules about how somebody's price is
calculated and it was based on a lot of
different factors I'm not sure I could
write a test case for that because I
don't know if I could look at the
situation say okay based on the inputs
this guy should be getting an 8%
discount is it possible to when the rule
set is quite large to really know what
the answer should be it is maybe for
large cases if you are talking about
end-to-end tests it's hard to cover all
scenarios yes but you can still test
rules individually as you would do unit
testing in a traditional programming
language and then define your set of
integration cases where you actually
execute all the rules and then get the
results and make sure they they match
what the expected value is would that be
more of iterative process where you run
them you look at the audit log the
business analyst looks at and says yeah
that's how we want it to work that's the
right answer for coming up with the use
cases yes but the idea is to automate
those tests as you automate any other
Lane
which is tasks so you have an automated
process that loads the data execute the
rules and then compares the results with
the expected results I can see the when
you are creating those test cases the
analysts could use the audit log to come
up with the with the individual cases
that they are they want to past okay now
let's talk about the engine itself you
talked about the thousands to tens of
thousands rules how many facts would a
application have with that size of rules
it again comes from even cases where you
have just a few facts a handful of facts
two cases where you have more than a
medium facts in memory in the ancient
executing concurrently the differences
are for online applications like you
know web applications where you have
services then usually it's a small set
of facts and you have many of those
requests coming in parallel and
executing in parallel for cases where
you are heading more towards complexity
and processing where you have stateful
rules working there usually you need all
the state presence so that you can
reason over the state so you have
millions of facts all the time in the
engine being evaluated concurrently you
talked about complex event processing a
couple times can you define what that is
complex event processing is is
discipline in in our area that deals
with processing of events the very if we
if we go very academic basically what it
does it's it detects patterns on stream
of events and then generates higher
level events from those patterns when
they are matched now if we bring this
into the rules context what complex
event processing does is adds the
real-time component to the solution
because when you are not dealing with
events you were basically processing
requests or your processing batches of
operations the
complex event processing allows you to
monitor real-time events in streams of
events and then make decisions based on
those streams of events okay in the
first case we're talking about we have
got all the data you hit submit and
we're going to think about it and tell
you the answer but the latter case might
be this might be something like what
comes up in monitoring the monitoring
software I've generally dealt with it
can only reason about something going on
on a single instance but I might not
care if I have 50 servers if one of them
has high load or is running out of space
I might want to know our 5 or more of
the servers experiencing high load for 3
minutes or more is that the type of case
where I could use complex event
processing yes that's that's the type of
case and you can do optimizations as
well if you use you know there is a part
of the rules engine that deals with
optimizations and then based on this you
can start predicting those loads and
saying well this server is going up so
before it reaches that level I will take
action and move some applications to
another cluster hmm you talked about
complex event processing and stateful
situations talk a bit more what is the
state that is involved in complex event
processing how does that differ from the
request or the decision service
application in the decision service or
the request based application you take
up a load of data payload reason about
them returns the response and then you
don't need that data anymore so it's
called this is usually implemented as
stateless right you throw away the next
request you'll be self contained in the
stateful cases what you mentioned I am
monitoring servers and I need to be
aware all the time of what is happening
and what happened during the last acts
time so the time window might be hours
days months so that data needs to be
available to the ancients so it can
reason over it's not something that I am
throwing away every time I
receive a new event I have to keep that
so that's the stateful part if we're
talking about five or more servers are
in some kind of critical state then you
would need to know the state of all the
servers and how long they've been in
that state so you know when two minutes
has expired but then one of them was in
a critical state for one minute then it
went back to normal so it's now so you
need to track these states as they
change is that right that's correct and
even when you are going to take action
on a server you need to know which other
server or which other cluster can I move
this application to so you have to be
aware of your whole context so it's a
context aware application in order to
execute those those tasks is it the case
that you have more the decisions or is
more a large number of rules fewer
effects and complex event processing you
might have millions effects but
relatively fewer rules does it work that
way yes that's very common especially
because of the requirements of the state
for cases it's very common to split the
the rule base into multiple rule base or
multiple knowledge bases so you end up
reducing the amount of rules so that you
can deal with more data and then each
part of your process or each node of
your even processing network will will
deal with a a part of the reasoning
process the case the decision service
case where you have tens of thousands of
rules how how long does it take for the
decision service to finish executing and
give you an answer it depends on the
complexity of the rules is like in a
database you have you know very complex
queries or very simple queries but the
requirements that we see nowadays is
typically under second response times
that's pretty amazing if you can reach a
decision involving tens of thousands of
rules in less than a second yeah
I've been involved in in a project late
last year where we had up to 3 million
rules and we had to respond in in up to
200 microseconds and and we did that in
in a very small harder so it's possible
the optimizations are really good there
in the case of complex event processing
I might not have many there not many
websites that have more than thousands
of servers but you could have
temperature sensors where there's a or
motion sensors where there's a enormous
number of them what are the memory
requirements for the state in cases like
sensors what typically happens is you
have to split for larger cases you have
to split this in phases so the first
phase is basically throws away the
majority of the events you are not
looking for because sensors generate
typically a lot of events so you have a
pre-filter phase where the majority of
the events you are not looking for is
thrown away and then you have a next
phase in your in your network there
where the events that might be
interesting to you are actually
processed so by doing this in phases you
can reduce the workload to levels that
are you know feasible in current hardier
little while ago you mentioned the two
types of inference which I know from a
little research on this topic there's
forward chaining and backward chaining
you explain what those are yes and and
that's exactly what they are so forward
chaining is the example we used where
the reasoning is driven by data so I
have a customer with more than 10
transactions so I flagged this customer
as a gold because this is a gold
customer then I will apply a discount to
him so this is a typical example of
forward chaining or or data driven
reasoning the other one backward
chaining is is the classic logic
programming or go driven reasoning where
you have goals that you want to achieve
in those goals they drive the reasoning
process so it's not data but its goals
an example would be I want to define you
know a route for my truck but this route
should use roads that are you know known
to have less traffic and then checking
those those roads is a soup goal of that
reasoning process so I change those
rules in terms of goals that they want
to achieve
instead of data that they have to reason
over
the Drule support both types of
inference yes Dru's is a hybrid engine
and you can mix and match the both types
of chaining inside even the same rules
so the same rule has conditions some of
those conditions can be data-driven some
of them can be goal-oriented so backward
and forward chaining if I understand is
in backward chaining it would work
backwards from the result to the facts
and it's searching for enough facts
somewhere that allow it to synthesize
the goal yes that's a perfect
description okay and so at programming
would I go in to the drools rules and
I'm writing and say from this point this
is a backward chain from this node here
in the in the technical language in the
native language we use a exclamation
point character to indicate which of
those conditions are backward chaining
basically so there is a little symbol
exclamation point in the in the in the
pattern that indicates that to the
engine I want to execute this as a
backward chaining everything else is
forward chaining typically developers
they have an easier time with forward
chaining so this is the most user type
for academic cases is a lot of them are
backward chaining but we support both
I'm aware there are programming
languages like Prolog that have built-in
backward chaining and it's been around
in academia for many years but
hasn't gotten much commercial traction
do you have any idea why why that is I
think it's the the target I mean when
you talk about actual business rules the
rules that we implement in in business
application enterprise applications most
of them are easier to implement in
forward chaining so that's why
production rules for road chaining
ancients they they basically dominate
the market prologue is one of the first
backward chaining languages and has been
around for a long time but it's really
used in cases that are more query driven
more research driven or if we're talking
about even like for fun algorithms like
a pseudo coup is over
so the coup is over would be much more
efficient implemented in backward
chaining them forward chaining but
typical business rules they are more
efficient in forward chaining okay now
in reading about this I ran across a lot
of discussion of the ricci algorithm and
I think we've already talked about it a
little bit but I want to ask you first
does it stand for something or is Riccio
word if I remember correctly it means
network in some language I apologize I
don't remember exactly but it the reason
it's famous is because it was the first
general-purpose algorithm that was able
to scale to the levels that that it does
for business rules one thing we have to
differentiate is that this algorithm was
written in 78 was published in 78 the
year I was born so it's as old as me but
there are many versions after that in
different algorithms that were based on
that that have optimizations on top of
it so really was the very first the most
famous one when we were talking earlier
about the engine builds an efficient
indexing structure that changed the
rules together in an optimal order was
that the ricci algorithm the basics of
the network the basics of the data
structure are really the optimization
we talked about like indexing you know
hashing note sharing those are things
that came after by the different
researchers they published papers on
them and they are typically implemented
in engines that follow that path are
there any real competitors to receive
that that are not simply extensions of
ricci but uh alternatives that are
fundamentally different for forward
chaining really was the best
general-purpose algorithm there are
there are others that are not applicable
to the general general problems they
have niche applications for instance
leaps was like this what happened is
over the years more and more
optimizations were done to the ricci
algorithm and it was morphed into things
other things so there are derivatives
that are better or as good as really but
the fundamentals of how how the
algorithm works came from really even
the outter that first published really
he created really two and rafi three
after that and other algorithms but the
the fundamentals are the same okay now I
want to get into JBoss the product
product you work on and the JBoss rules
engine start starting with what is JBoss
so JBoss is a division of Red Hat for
mid or so all the middle products you
know Java implementations from Red Hat
come from this division from from JBoss
it was a company it was acquired back in
2006 by Red Hat but all the the midler
products are under that division it was
the relationship between drools and
JBoss drools is a project of JBoss so
Druce was JBoss Red Hat they hired most
of the drools developers over the years
and built a team so that team works on
developing the business rules engine
one common question is because JBoss
application server is very famous has
been around for a long time so a lot of
people when they talk about J buzz they
immediately immediately think about the
application server the application
server is one project under the JBoss
umbrella drools is another project and
jbpm is another project and so on so
forth
in jbpm that's a Business Process
Management yes and that does raise a
question we had a show on workflow
management systems a while back can you
clarify the distinction between a
workflow management and a rules engine
and I understand the case where you have
a decision service you ask it a question
that could be a step in the business
process but some of these complex event
processing cases where there are events
happening that's starting to sound a
little more like a business process but
is there a clear distinction between the
two there is basically the easiest way
to say is you know Business Process
Management solutions in jbpm they they
implement workflows they implement
processes so processes are usually
things that happen in steps and you have
a very clear flow rules on the other
side or decision services they are more
unstructured they define scenarios when
those scenarios are found or are matched
something happens they execute an action
or they return a value right but if we
look at business applications in the
modeling of logic you basically have
four pillars if you will one is ontology
x' that's the model how you build the
domain model of an application then you
have the business processes that define
the structure the very well-defined flow
of actions that have to happen the roles
that are the own structure actions that
have to be taken based on scenarios and
the complex event processing that's
basically the real-time component
in all those four pillars they have to
work together and we have a very close
relationship with jbpm we use the same
API we we use algorithms integrated in
there so we work together to try to
provide this solution that allows users
to model business problems basically it
sounds like very powerful modeling tools
when you get all those combined yes it
basically allows you to define business
logic outside imperative application
code and that is is very powerful with
it a deal I can't stress enough the
importance that life cycle or the
independent life cycle has on on how
agile those companies can go how they
can decrease time to market and so on so
forth I'm not going to much details here
but yeah
okay now I'm setting up the JBoss rules
are there other tools like IDE a
debugger things that will help in the
development process yes we have a plugin
for Eclipse in terms of IDE so you can
use Eclipse to develop the rules you can
you know the bug set breakpoints inspect
variables things like this our main
tooling is is based on a web application
so it's web tooling
where you can define rules and inside
the same tool you can define processes
as well and models as well so our main
tools are web-based but we do have
Eclipse plugin for ID do you treat the
rules more like code where the rules
might be checked in to get and their
version controlled and then they go
through a test cycle or the rules more
like data elements in a database where
you could deploy a new rule by
essentially doing an insert into some
kind of store both we do use code
versioning
Trobe behind the scenes so we do use git
for instances repository it has the
tasks life cycling etc but the engine
allows the rules to be treated as data
from an application point of view so you
can redeploy rules at any time without
stopping the application are always
completely dynamic it's live all the
time when you redeploy a new rule the
new rule takes effect and there is no
need for downtime one more question that
that we can wrap up with in the early
days of artificial intelligence when
perhaps researchers were much more
optimistic about the field it was
believed that any kind of expertise or
human intelligence could be reduced to
rules so that researchers would go
around and interview experts and say
things like mr. expert or dr. expert how
did you make this medical diagnosis and
very diligently write down all the rules
then they found that this didn't really
capture it because the experts were
maybe not cooperating and they would not
be able to explain all the rules it's a
yes but there's this exception as a
researcher named Dreyfus who wrote a
couple of books on this one of them is
called what computers can't do and he
disputed that rules could really capture
human expertise and now in the last few
years we've had this explosion of
machine learning techniques neural nets
which are data-driven or something like
neural nets where you don't really have
a model a cognitive model of how the
decision is made so I'm wondering do we
see maybe chaining together of you know
a machine learning step with a
classifier that creates facts that then
you can analyze these facts with rules
and how did all these things play
together in the modern world it's a very
interesting field there are many many
applications where you can combine those
technologies or those researchers to
produce very
amazing results for if we are looking at
businesses I think this is much more
advanced in what business usually needs
but there is a number of things that
could be achieved with that having said
that I think the current understanding
of the market is that it's more
important at the moment to provide
systems that support decisions then
systems that take this that make
decisions by themselves so there is a
lot of research in terms of you know the
supported clinical decisions or
supported you know law making decisions
but this is really on supporting people
and people would look at those
conclusions and then derive their own
conclusions from that I don't see much
in terms of replacing completely or
automating completely those complex
decisions as it was thought it would be
possible in the Golden Age of you know
AI the case of decision support with an
example of that B then the physician
might entered clinical signs and
symptoms and the system come back and
say here's some possible diagnosis the
doctor still is gonna look at it and say
I'm here I know it's this or it's not
that but you are hopefully suggesting
something the doctor might not have
thought of that's that's basically the
idea but more importantly the system we
even tell you these are the
possibilities but if for instance you
ask for this other exam from the from
the patient then you can exclude from
the results of the exams these options
here or you can confirm that one so
basically the the system would lay out
the map for the physician so that the
physician physician can you know
understand better where where he is or
help him find where he is in that
situation so let's go back to the
business example I'm sure that the
company that's giving loans has a lot of
rules and you could decide whether to
give someone Lone Rock based on the
rules but I'm wondering if they came up
with all those rules
because that was the only way to do it
or they didn't have a better way and if
the goal is to give loans to people who
will pay them back and not to give loans
to people who default would perhaps a
machine learning approach give you a
better loan performance than rules do we
know for specifically for the insurance
industry what I've seen more is is
really driven by requirements and by
policies of the company but there are
areas where it's not really possible to
define those rules in advance and those
rules are mined very easy examples you
go into Amazon website and you make a
purchase and then next time you go to
the website it will suggest other
products maybe you read you didn't even
thought about those other products but
they fit your profile it's something
that you would like to have and those
are rule-based systems but the rules are
created based on you know extraction of
data and machine learning
great well we've covered a lot of
material here is there anything else
you'd like to add that we haven't talked
about oh I think it's the area is a
passion of mine I I recommend you know
anyone interested to join us in the
community talk discuss you know look for
topics that interest them we are always
happy to to to talk but that's it thank
you very much for having me it was a
pleasure and if people would like to
learn more about you do you write blog
Twitter where can people go the truth
stop org website is the entry point and
from there you can you have the URLs for
the blog you have the URLs for the
chatroom for the mailing list for
everything so drools dot org and then
from there you'll find everything you
need great Edson thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
thank you for software engineering radio
this has been Robert Bluman
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening